After what happened today,
بعد ما حدث اليوم
we can be certain that Cui Jun
...يمكننا التأكد من أن تسوي جيون
wasn't abducted by Grand Tutor Xie.
لم يُختطف على يد المعلم الأكبر شيه
Otherwise,
وإلا
he wouldn't have made a deal with me
لما كان سيستخدم رسالة من أمي
just because of a letter from my mother.
ليعقد صفقة معي
If Cui Jun were in his hands,
لو كان تسوي جيون معه حقًا
he could have simply grilled him
وأراد معرفة حقيقة قضية عشيرتي آن ولو
for the truth behind the An and Lu families' case.
لكان استجوبه مباشرة
I know your little brain has become much sharper than before,
أعلم أن عقلك الصغير أذكى بكثير من ذي قبل
but it needs some rest now.
لكنه يحتاج للراحة الآن
Stop thinking about it.
لا تفكري في الأمر
Yummy.
لذيذ
Back when we were on the march,
في الماضي أثناء المسيرات العسكرية
all we could eat were flatbreads or dried meat,
كنا نأكل الفطائر أو اللحم المجفف فقط
and occasionally finding some wild greens would satisfy our cravings.
أحيانًا كنا نجد بعض الخضروات البرية لإشباع شهيتنا
Now that you don't have much of an appetite
الآن ليس لديكِ شهية لتناول الطعام
and can't eat meat while in mourning,
ولا يجوز تناول اللحوم في فترة الحداد
you could try this first.
لذا جربي هذا أولًا
I've had wild-green flatbreads before,
لقد أكلت فطائر الخضروات البرية من قبل
but I've never had ones this delicious.
لكنني لم أذق شيئًا بهذه اللذة قط
Surely Qing Long couldn't have made these.
تشينغ لونغ بالتأكيد لا يعرف كيف يصنعها
Please thank Yan Yue for me.
اشكر الأخت الكبرى يان يوه بالنيابة عني
Okay.
حسنًا
You are Crown Prince Wenxi.
أنت ولي عهد ونشي
In terms of blood relations,
وفقًا لعلاقة الدم
you should be
فأنت الشخص الأقرب إلى أمي
the person closest to my mother in this world.
في هذا العالم
Emperor Wenxi was my mother's elder brother,
إمبراطور ونشي هو شقيق أمي
so you should call her...
إذًا يجب أن تنادي والدتي
Aunt.
بعمتك
But compared to me,
لكن مقارنة بي
even though you aren't Princess Yunzhao's biological daughter,
على الرغم من أنكِ لستِ ابنة الأميرة
you are her true family.
إلا أنكِ عائلتها الحقيقية
There's no need for you to tell me that.
لستُ بحاجة لأن تخبرني بذلك
Blood ties are merely where one comes from,
صلة القرابة تحدد من أين يأتي الإنسان
but not where one belongs.
لكنها لا تحدد إلى أين ينتمي
A marriage brought about by the pressure of the imperial family,
بسبب زواج تم تحت ضغط العائلة الإمبراطورية
and one that had to be maintained in order to bind the aristocratic clans
والذي كان لا مفر من الحفاظ عليه من أجل الربط بين العائلات الأرستقراطية
and the imperial family together,
والأسرة الحاكمة
ultimately wasted half the lives of both Princess Yunzhao and Grand Tutor.
ضاع في النهاية نصف عمر الأميرة والمعلم الأكبر
I hope that this time,
آمل أن تتمكني هذه المرة
you can help Princess Yunzhao find the freedom she deserved.
من تحقيق الحرية للأميرة
You sure sound convincing,
أنت تتحدث بمنطق شديد
yet you're not exactly any better yourself.
لكنك لست أفضل حالًا
What?
ماذا؟
I mean,
...أقول
without any witnesses,
إذا لم يكن هناك شاهد
how can we bring the murderer
فكيف يمكن
who killed my mother to justice?
تقديم قاتل أمي للعدالة؟
Isn't there already a rumor going around
أليس الجميع يقولون
that I killed Princess Yunzhao to seize the Phoenix Heart Token?
إنني قتلت الأميرة من أجل الحصول على أمر تشيوه قو؟
Let's fan the flames.
فلندع هذه النار تشتعل بقوة أكبر
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[مفتاح قلب العنقاء]
[Episode 18]
[الحلقة الثامنة عشر]
Since I harboured prejudices against the An and Lu families,
بسبب تحيزي ضد عشيرتي آن ولو
I never truly listened to what was in your heart,
لم أستمع أبدًا لصوت قلبك الحقيقي
♪ I traded obsession for this loss ♪
♪ خسارةٌ جلبها الإصرار المتشبث ♪
thinking it was merely your obsession.
ظننت أن ذلك مجرد هوس منك
♪ If I could lay my heart bare and cross ♪
♪ لو استطعتُ أن أشقّ هذا القلب ♪
I always firmly believed that you were the one who had wronged me,
لطالما آمنت بأنك خذلتني
♪ Would you once more have pity on me ♪
♪ فهل كنتَ سترأف بي مرةً أخرى؟ ♪
but I never realized that I had wronged you as well.
لكن لم أفكر أبدًا أنني خذلتك أيضًا
I suspect that 25 years ago,
أشك أنه قبل خمسة وعشرين عامًا
♪ If the heavens should change and fate tear me apart ♪
♪ ولو تغيّرت السماء فجأةً ومزّقني القدر إربًا ♪
the real Cui Jun had already been killed,
قُتل تسوي جيون الحقيقي بالفعل
♪ Yet still cannot undo one beat of my heart's art ♪
♪ لكن ذلك لن يُحطّم لحظةً واحدة من الشوق ♪
and that the man who survived was a secret agent from Northern Qin.
والذي عاش بعد ذلك كان جاسوسًا من تشين الشمالية
If that's the case, then perhaps there's more to
لذلك فإن قضية عشيرتي آن ولو التي كشف عنها آنذاك
♪ I've traveled so far— the day I find you again ♪
♪ سرتُ دروبًا بعيدةً وشاقة حتى أتى يومُ لُقياك من جديد
the An and Lu families' crime he exposed back then than meets the eye.
ربما كانت وراءها حقيقة أخرى
♪ I fear you might have forgotten me ♪
♪ أخشى أن تنسى ♪
He refuses to speak now,
هو يرفض التحدث الآن
but I've brought him back to Jiankang.
لكنني أحضرته إلى جيانكانغ
♪ I fear no doom of endless karmic pain ♪
♪ لا أخشى حقًا الوقوع في الجحيم الأبدي ♪
Whether or not I can clear the An and Lu families' name,
سواء تمكنت من إثبات براءة عشيرتي آن ولو أم لا
♪ Only that you drift far from my side ♪
♪ أخشى فقط أن تبتعد عني ♪
at least this time,
على الأقل هذه المرة
♪ Apart from you, the world is an endless night ♪
♪ إذا فارقتك فلن يبقى في هذا العالم سوى الليل الأبدي ♪
I'm standing with you.
أنا أقف في صفك
♪ Even if my beating heart wears thin and fades ♪
♪ حتى ولو نبض القلب سيبذل قصارى جهده ♪
We were once husband and wife.
لقد كنا زوجين ذات يوم
May all past grievances be laid to rest,
لذلك أتمنى أن تزول ضغائننا وخلافاتنا مستقبلًا
♪ I'd choose this fate till death's final line ♪
♪ فسأظل راضيًا حتى الموت ♪
and may you no longer be trapped by the past.
وأنت أيضًا لا يجب أن تظل حبيس الماضي
♪ I only hope the mortal lands ♪
♪ كل ما أتمناه أن يمنحني هذا العالم ♪
♪ Can grant our wishes ♪
♪ تحقيق أمنيتك وأمنيتي ♪
♪ Through endless night, let heaven and earth fall apart ♪
♪ حتى لو كان بيننا ليل أبدي وحتى لو تحطم العالم بأسره ♪
♪ Just to gaze upon you one last time ♪
♪ لأراك مرة أخرى ♪
Grand Tutor.
المعلم الأكبر
I told you
لقد أخبرتك عن
about Li Mao's background
حقيقة لي ماو
to warn you about the situation,
لأحذّرك من الوضع القائم
not so you could
وليس لأجعلكِ
kill my wife!
تقتلين زوجتي
You're the one who truly fails to understand the situation!
الشخص الذي لم يفهم الوضع حقًا هو أنت
Crown Prince Wenxi isn't dead at all,
ولي عهد ونشي لم يمت أبدًا
and they still have the Phoenix Heart Token!
وما زال بحوزتهم أمر تشيوه قو
What did you say?
ماذا تقولين؟
If Princess Yunzhao had returned alive,
إذا كانت الأميرة عادت حية
my brother would have had no chance of survival.
لما كان لأخي أي أمل في النجاة
What other option did I have?
فماذا عساي أن أفعل؟
I wouldn't spare anyone
كل من قد يشكل خطرًا عليه
who might pose a threat to him.
لن أرحمه أبدًا
Grand Tutor.
أيها المعلم الأكبر
Mao.
أخي
Let's go.
هيا بنا
What's this supposed to mean?
ما الذي تقصدينه بهذا؟
I said I'd give you this as a gift.
إنه السيف الذي قلت لك إنني سأهديه لك
It's made of black iron, which is even tougher than refined iron.
إنه من الذهب الأسود وهو أصلب من الحديد المكرر
It won't rust or corrode for 100 years,
لا يصدأ ولا يتآكل حتى بعد مئة عام
and it's 100 times more powerful than Eagle King's Longque Blade.
وهو أقوى بمئة مرة من سيف التنين الثمين الخاص بأمير النسر
When did you forge it?
متى صقلتِه؟
Before we left for Guazhou.
قبل الذهاب إلى قواتشو
But it didn't have a scabbard back then.
لكن في ذلك الوقت لم يكن له غمد بعد
I specifically asked
لقد طلبت خصيصًا
Master Wei from Yunyan Pavilion
من المعلم الأكبر وي من جناح يونيان
to craft one for this sword.
أن يصنع غمدًا مناسبًا لهذا السيف الثمين
Well? Do you like it?
ما رأيك؟ هل أعجبك؟
I'm sure
...أظن
you wouldn't just give this to me for nothing.
أنكِ لن تهديني إياه بهذه البساطة
By the banks of the Qushui River, there's a mountain called Mount Fengming.
على ضفاف نهر تشوشوي يوجد جبل يدعى جبل فنغمينغ
It offers a broad view,
من هناك يمكن رؤية منظر واسع
and when the weather is clear,
عندما يكون الطقس جيدًا
you can see the rolling mountain ranges.
يمكن رؤية سلسلة الجبال الممتدة
Behind those ranges
وخلف سلسلة الجبال تلك
lies my mother's former fief,
تقع الأرض التي كانت إقطاعية أمي سابقًا
Yunzhao Prefecture.
مقاطعة يونتشاو
Though, unfortunately, it later fell under the control of Northern Qin.
لكن للأسف، أصبحت لاحقًا تابعة لتشين الشمالية
So?
إذًا؟
So I want to buy this mountain
لذا، أريد شراء هذا الجبل
and make it my mother's burial site.
ليكون قبرًا لأمي
However,
لكن
it is currently owned by a wealthy local family,
هذه الأرض الآن ملك عائلة ثرية محلية
and they're asking for a very high price.
والسعر المطلوب مرتفع للغاية
I've scraped together what I can,
لقد جمعت ما أملك من مال
but I'm still short by this little bit.
ولكن ما زال ينقصني القليل
Don't worry, I'm not borrowing it for free.
لا تقلق، لن آخذه بالمجان
I've already paid you interest.
لقد أعطيتك الفائدة بالفعل
How much are you short?
كم ينقصكِ؟
Five thousand taels.
خمسة آلاف ليانغ
Don't tell me
لا يمكن
that the dignified Heir of Prince Jing'an, commander of Beifu,
ولي عهد أمير جينغآن المبجل وقائد جيش الشمال
can't even come up with
لا يستطيع حتى تدبير مبلغ زهيد
a mere 5,000 taels.
مثل خمسة آلاف ليانغ؟
My father owns a small forested mountain on the outskirts of the capital.
والدي لديه غابة صغيرة في ضواحي العاصمة
The fengshui there is no worse than that of Mount Fengming.
موقعها لا يقل جودة عن جبل فنغمينغ
I'd be happy to gift it to Princess Yunzhao.
أنا ميتعد أن أمنحها للأميرة
If you don't want to lend it, just say so.
إذا كنت لا تريد إقراضي، فقل ذلك
Why go to all that trouble with lies?
لماذا تختلق كل هذه الأكاذيب؟
Your Highness, why did you suddenly decide to clean the horse today?
يا ولي العهد، لماذا قررت فجأة غسل الحصان اليوم؟
Your Highness, it's all here.
يا ولي العهد، هذا كل ما لدينا
You've invested all your personal savings in the army,
لقد استثمرت كل مدخراتك الخاصة في الجيش
leaving only this small amount on you.
ولم يتبقَّ لك إلا هذا المبلغ
It's only a bit over 3,000 taels.
ما يقارب ثلاثة آلاف ليانغ فقط
The dignified Heir of Prince Jing'an
ولي عهد أمير جينغآن المبجل
only has 3,000 taels of personal savings—
مدخراته الخاصة ثلاثة آلاف ليانغ فقط
no one would believe that if word got out.
إذا علم أحد بهذا مستحيل أن يصدق
Sell this red steed,
بيعي حصاني تشي جيوي
then exchange all of this for cash
وحولي كل هذه إلى فضة نقدية
and give it to He Yuanji.
وأعطيها إلى خه يوان جي
Have her withdraw my entire share
ثم اجعليها تسحب حصتي من ممتلكات العائلة
from the family estate
بأكملها
and give it all to Xie Jiayu.
وتعطيها كلها إلى شيه جيا يوي
Just tell her it's a loan from the Prince's household.
وتقول لها إنها قرض من قصر الأمير
But this is the prized Western Regions steed your father, His Highness, gave you,
لكن هذا حصان والدك الأمير الأكبر الذي أهداه لك من المناطق الغربية
1 in 10,000.
حصان أصيل لا مثيل له
You won't find another one like it in all of Ye.
لا يوجد مثله في كل مملكة يه الكبرى
You wouldn't even bear to ride it onto the battlefield.
لدرجة أنك لم تطاوعك نفسك على ركوبه في ساحة المعركة
Sell it.
سأبيعه
Why didn't you try to talk him out of it?
قومي بإقناعه
Why should I?
بماذا أقنعه؟
Everything in this world has a price, but affection is priceless.
كل شيء له ثمن، إلا المشاعر فهي لا تقدر بثمن
Don't you know what matters more
ألا تعرف جيدًا
in His Highness's heart?
ما هو الأهم في قلب الأمير؟
Back when he used to toss money to Master Yuan,
في السابق، حين كان يُغدق بالمال على المعلم يوان
at least you could hear it clink.
كان يحظى على الأقل بصدىً لصدقته
Now he doesn't even reveal his name.
أما الآن فما عاد اسمه يُذكر حتى
You fool.
!يا لغبائك
Can't you think of a way
ألا يمكنك إيجاد طريقة
to let Lady Xie know?
لإعلام السيدة شيه؟
Lady Xie?
!السيدة شيه
I heard that when I was severely injured after receiving a flogging,
سمعت أنني بعد جلدي مرضت بشدة
it was Your Highness who paid for the purchase of precious medicinal herbs
وأن سموكِ من دفعتِ لشراء الأدوية الثمينة
to treat me.
لعلاجي
It must have cost Your Highness a lot.
وكانت التكلفة باهظة
Since I can't pay you back right now,
لا أستطيع سدادها الآن
I offer this deed of debt
هذا هو سند الدين
as proof
ليكون دليلًا على ذلك
that I'll surely repay the debt someday.
وسأرده لكِ في المستقبل
It was merely a small favor.
إنه مجرد معروف بسيط
One should not accept rewards without merit.
لا يصح قبول العطاء دون تقديم عون
The life-saving kindness Your Highness has shown me is far too great.
إن فضلك يا زوجة ولي العهد في إنقاذ حياتي عظيم جدًا
A great favor can become a burden like an enemy's debt.
والدين العظيم قد يصبح عبئًا كالعداوة
I'd rather bear a debt
أفضل أن أكون مدينًا بالمال
than carry the weight of your kindness.
على أن أكون مدينًا بمعروف
Sorry for offending you that day.
لقد كنت وقحًا في ذلك اليوم
The distinction between nobles and commoners and the differences in people's hearts...
الفارقُ بين النبلاء والعامة كالفارق بين بواطن القلوب
You aristocratic traitors—
العائلات الأرستقراطية التي تخون الوطن
you're parasites feeding off our country!
إنهم آفة الأمة
Are not something a woman like Your Highness could overcome.
لم يكن من الصواب أن أصب غضبي
I shouldn't have taken my anger out on Your Highness.
على امرأة مثلك يا زوجة ولي العهد
I hereby apologize to Your Highness.
أعتذر لكِ يا زوجة ولي العهد
How do you plan
كل هذا المال
to pay this much money back?
كيف تنوي سداده؟
By copying books, or selling my calligraphy—
سأنسخ الكتب وأبيع الخطوط التي أكتبها
I'll find a way.
سأجد طريقة ما
Let's go.
هيا
Qing Long?
تشينغ لونغ
Why are you taking the red steed out of the mansion?
لماذا تأخذ تشي جيوي خارج القصر؟
His Highness asked me to sell it.
طلب مني ولي العهد أن أبيع الحصان
Sell it?
!تبيعه
Yes. His Highness told me not to say anything.
نعم، ولي العهد أمرني ألا أُخبر أحدًا
Please pretend you didn't see it, Your Highness.
يا زوجة ولي العهد، اعتبري أنك لم تري شيئًا
Nanxing.
نان شينغ
bring out my short dagger.
أحضري خنجري القصير
My Lady,
سيدتي
but Her Highness
لكنه
left it to you for self-defense.
الشيء الذي تركته لكِ الأميرة لتحمي نفسك به
I've got no choice. I'm broke.
أنا فقيرة
Take these out and ask around how much they're worth.
خذي هذه الأشياء للخارج واسألي عن سعرها
If the price is reasonable, just pawn them all.
إذا كان السعر مناسبًا فبيعيها كلها
I'll figure out a way to make up the rest.
سأفكر في طريقة لتدبر الباقي
If we pawn Miraculous Craft as well,
إذا رهنتُ اليد البارعة
it should probably be enough.
أعتقد أن هذا سيكون كافيًا
Is His Highness really unwilling to lend you the money?
هل يرفض ولي العهد إقراضك المال حقًا؟
That's really stingy of him.
إنه بخيل جدًا
He's the commander of Beifu, after all.
قائد جيش الشمال العظيم
Didn't he just confiscate the Cui family's mines?
ألم يصادر منجم عائلة تسوي مؤخرًا؟
Those were confiscated on behalf of the court.
لقد صادره نيابة عن البلاط الإمبراطوري
They're not the Xiao family's private property.
وليس ملكية خاصة لعائلة شياو
Still, I never expected
لكنني لم أتوقع
Xiao Wuyi wouldn't even lend me 5,000 taels.
أن شياو وو يي سيرفض حتى إقراضي خمسة آلاف ليانغ
I thought he would at least...
...ظننت أنه على الأقل
Xie Jiayu,
شيه جيا يوي
I'm smitten with you.
أنا أحبك
Talking about being smitten with me.
ماذا كان يقصد بأنه يحبني؟
Forget it.
انسِ الأمر
In the end, I only have myself to rely on.
على المرء أن يعتمد على نفسه في الحياة
Yuanji.
الأخت يوان جي
This is...
...هذا
I'm lending this to you on behalf of Prince Jing'an's Household.
هذا قرض من قصر الأمير
Take it and choose any place you like
يمكنكِ اختيار أي مكان يعجبكِ
as Princess Yunzhao's burial site.
لتضعي فيه قبر الأميرة
The Heir has been fighting battles all over the country these past years.
خاض ولي العهد حروبًا في الجنوب والشمال طوال هذه السنوات
Although he hasn't spent much on himself,
ورغم أنه لا ينفق الكثير من المال على نفسه
Beifu's expenditures have been enormous.
إلا أن نفقات جيش الشمال ضخمة
He's poured all his salary into the army.
وقد استثمر كل راتبه في الجيش
The expenses of Prince Jing'an's Household
أما بالنسبة لنفقات قصر أمير جينغآن
have been completely supported by me and the Princess Consort.
فأنا والأميرة نتكفل بها
We truly cannot count on the Heir and Prince Jing'an.
لا يمكننا الاعتماد على ولي العهد والأمير الأكبر حقًا
I oversee Prince Jing'an's Household's accounts,
أنا أدير حسابات قصر أمير جينغآن
and the Heir is indeed short on funds.
وولي العهد يعاني من ضائقة مالية بالفعل
I'm being completely honest.
يمكنني أن أكون صريحة معكِ يا أختي
Then where did this money come from?
إذًا، من أين أتى هذا المال؟
The Heir had Ferghana horse.
لدى ولي العهد حصان من سلالة الخيول العرقية
I heard it was a gift from Prince Jing'an
سمعت أنه عندما انتصر في معركته الأولى
when he won his first battle.
أهداه إياه الأمير الأكبر
That horse had a pure bloodline and was priceless.
ذلك الحصان من سلالة نقية ولا يقدر بثمن
A few days ago, I saw Qing Long
قبل بضعة أيام، رأيت تشينغ لونغ
lead it away to be sold,
يأخذه ليبيعه
along with some land deeds and shop deeds.
وهناك أيضًا بعض صكوك الأراضي والدكاكين
All together, this is how much was raised.
وبجمعها معًا، تمكن من جمع هذا المبلغ
The Heir even kept it from me too.
لقد أخفى ولي العهد الأمر عني أيضًا
He only told me to send the money over.
وطلب مني فقط أن أسلمكِ المال
Do you know what the two largest expenses
هل تعلمين خلال العام الماضي
under the Heir's name in the household
ما هما أكبر نفقتين في القصر
were in the past year?
تم تسجيلهما باسم ولي العهد؟
What?
ما هما؟
The first was your wedding with the Heir—
الأولى هي حفل زفافك أنتِ وولي العهد
a fake wedding doomed to be ruined from the start.
ذلك الزواج المزيف الذي كان مقدرًا له أن يتحطم
Well, a fake act has to be made
تلك المسرحية المزيفة
convincing enough for people to believe it, right?
كان يجب أن تكون واقعية بما يكفي ليصدقها الناس
The second was the renovation
والثانية هي تجديد جناح تسانغفنغ
of this Cangfeng Forge after you moved into the mansion.
بعد دخولكِ القصر
This place used to be nothing more than
كان هذا المكان في الأصل مجرد
an empty room for storing sundries,
غرفة فارغة لتخزين الأغراض
abandoned for years.
وقد هُجر لسنوات طويلة
Didn't you notice
ألم تلاحظي
that the furnace outside was also renovated?
أن الموقد في الخارج قد تم تجديده أيضًا؟
No wonder.
...لا عجب
No wonder it looks so much like the one at my home.
لا عجب أنه يشبه كثيرًا ذلك الذي في منزلي
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
you sold your horse,
لقد بعت حصانك
but you didn't take the interest.
لكنك لم تأخذ الفائدة
Qing Long...
!تشينغ لونغ هذا
But this is not
ولكن ما أريده
what I want.
ليس هذا
What do you want then?
ماذا تريد؟
I'm not telling you.
لن أخبركِ
I don't want you to think of this
لا أريدكِ أن تشعري
as a transaction.
بأن هذه صفقة
Your Highness.
ولي العهد
The Empress Dowager is hosting a banquet.
الإمبراطورة الأرملة تقيم مأدبة في القصر
Under what pretext?
ما المناسبة؟
She claims
...تقول إن
Empress Wenxi
إمبراطورة ونشي
appeared in her dream,
ظهرت لها في المنام
asking Your Highness to bring the Phoenix Heart Token into the palace.
وطلبت من ولي العهد إحضار أمر تشيوه قو إلى القصر
All right.
حسنًا
She finally couldn't hold back any longer
أخيرًا لم تعد تستطيع الصبر
and came forward on her own.
وكشفت عن نفسها
Mother!
أمي
Why do people like you, high and mighty,
لماذا أنتم، أصحاب المكانة والنفوذ
always try to corner me and my brother?
تحبون دائمًا أن تدفعوني أنا وأخي إلى الزاوية؟
We simply want to survive.
كل ما نريده هو أن نعيش
Your Highness.
أيتها الأميرة
My brother has been so kind to Yaoyao.
أخي يعامل جيا يوي بلطف شديد
Why are you still unwilling to let him go?
لماذا ترفضين تركه وشأنه؟
Calm down!
اهدئي قليلًا
I never wanted Prince Qi dead!
لم أفكر قط في قتل أمير تشي
You hold the Phoenix Heart Token,
أمر تشيوه قو بين يديكِ
and you intend to support Crown Prince Wenxi.
وتريدين دعم ولي عهد ونشي
If he ever makes it to Jiankang,
إذا ذهب إلى جيانكانغ يومًا ما
will my brother have any chance of survival?
فهل سيظل أخي على قيد الحياة؟
Tell me,
أخبريني
where exactly is Crown Prince Wenxi hiding?
أين يختبئ ولي عهد ونشي بالضبط؟
There's no way I'll tell you that!
من المستحيل أن أخبركِ
Fine. Then let's take this secret with us
حسنًا، فلنختفِ نحن الاثنان
and vanish
من هذا العالم
from this world together!
ونحمل هذا السر معنا
Mao...
أخي
Lejun.
له جيون
Don't be afraid.
لا تخافي
Mao...
أخي
Do you remember
هل ما زلت تتذكر
when we were little,
عندما كنا صغارًا
wandering among displaced refugees?
وكنا نعيش بين اللاجئين؟
Back then,
في ذلك الوقت
whenever there was a single flatbread
إذا وجدنا رغيفًا واحدًا
or a bowl of porridge,
أو وعاء من العصيدة
you'd always let me have it.
كنت تعطيني أولًا لآكل
Whenever older children tried to bully me,
وإذا حاول الأولاد الأكبر إيذائي
you'd risk your life to protect me.
كنت تقاتلهم بكل قوتك لتحميني
Those memories aren't pleasant.
تلك الذكريات ليست جيدة
I've long forgotten them.
أخوكِ لا يتذكرها
But I haven't.
لكني أتذكرها
Although those days were harsh,
على الرغم من أن تلك الأيام كانت مريرة
they were the happiest time
لكن بالنسبة لي
of my life.
كانت سعيدة جدًا
Because even back then,
لأنني علمت منذ ذلك الوقت
I knew I had the best older brother in the entire world—
أن لديّ أفضل أخ في العالم
one who'd never let go of my hand,
...أخ
not even in death.
لن يترك يدي أبدًا حتى الموت
Mao.
أخي
I wasn't afraid then,
لم أكن خائفة آنذاك
and I'm even less afraid now.
أما الآن، فقد غدوتُ أقل خوفًا من ذي قبل
Mao.
أخي
I will protect you, no matter what.
سأحميك بالتأكيد
It's alright.
لقد انتهى الأمر
Don't be afraid.
لا تخافي
Yaoyao.
جيا يوي
Greetings, Princess Pingning.
تحياتي لأميرة بينغنينغ
Are you truly determined
أحقًا
to draw a line between us?
تريدين أن تبتعدي عني؟
Her Highness...
...الأميرة
Other than an admission of guilt,
ما لم يكن كلامك اعترافًا بالذنب
I never want to hear another word
لا أريد أن أسمع منكِ
about my mother from your lips.
أي شيء يتعلق بأمي مرة أخرى
We were once good friends.
كنا صديقتين يومًا
There's no need for such hollow pretenses between us.
فما الداعي للتظاهر؟
Yaoyao.
جيا يوي
You've truly grown up.
لقد كبرتِ
It's all because of you that I had to grow up.
أنتم جميعًا من أردتم مني أن أكبر
Do you really think
هل تعتقدين حقًا أن ما فعلتِه
your scheme was flawless?
كان مثاليًا؟
That day,
في ذلك اليوم
Her Highness and I both fell off the cliff.
سقطت أنا والأميرة من على الجبل
If not for a tree that caught me,
لولا أن شجرةً قد علِقت بي
I wouldn't have survived, either.
لما بقيت على قيد الحياة أيضًا
And it was Young Lord Xiao's men saved me.
أنقذني رجال ولي العهد شياو
M-My hand had only just healed.
يدي... لقد شُفيت يدي لتوي
To accuse me of trying to harm Princess Yunzhao
والقول بإنني قتلت الأميرة
is rather absurd.
هو أمرٌ يفيضُ سخافةً وعبثًا
If that's the case,
إذا كان الأمر كذلك
then why did you have Da snatch the coachman's family
فلماذا جعلتِ آ دا ينتزع عائلة سائس الخيل
from me?
من بين يدي؟
Were you afraid
هل كنتِ تخشين
they witnessed something they shouldn't have?
أن يكونوا قد رأوا شيئًا؟
But they didn't see anything.
لكنهم لم يروا شيئًا
Lejun.
له جيون
I truly hope it wasn't you.
لا أتمنى حقًا أن تكوني أنتِ
Because if it was,
لأنه لو كان كذلك
I'd be deeply disappointed in our friendship.
فسيصيبني خيبة أمل كبيرة في الصداقة
Yaoyao.
جيا يوي
I didn't expect you to enter the palace today.
لم أتوقع أن تأتي إلى القصر اليوم
Mao.
ماو
You knew I was using you
أنت تعلم أنني استغللتك
to test Li Lejun.
لاختبار لي له جيون
She's your sister.
إنها أختك
I believe you only learned about it afterwards.
أثق بأنك لم تعلم بالأمر إلا بعد وقوعه
I understand that you were put in a difficult position.
أتفهم موقفك الصعب
I don't blame you.
أنا لا ألومك
But please, don't make things difficult for me anymore either.
لكن أرجوك لا تصعب عليّ الأمور بعد الآن
Long live Your Majesty!
لتعش الإمبراطورة الأرملة ألف عام
You may rise, my beloved ministers.
ارفعوا التحية، يا وزرائي الكرام
Thank you, Your Majesty!
شكرًا للإمبراطورة الأرملة
Today, at this palace banquet,
اليوم، في مأدبة القصر هذه
I'd like to raise a toast with all my beloved ministers.
سأشرب كأسًا مع وزرائي الأوفياء
A few days ago, Empress Wenxi appeared to me in a dream,
قبل أيام، حلمت بإمبراطورة ونشي
and I've learned that the old prophecy—
وعلمت منها أن تلك النبوءة المتداولة
"when the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world"—
بظهور تشيوه قو سيستقر العالم
is no mere tale.
تبين على غير المتوقع أنها حقيقة
Two Phoenix Heart Tokens have been
فقد وُجد أمران من أوامر تشيوه قو
passed down to Princess Yunzhao and Cui Jun respectively.
أحدهما مع الأميرة والآخر مع تسوي جيون
That's enough.
كفى
My Lord,
أيها النبيل
what's the point of arresting me?
ما الفائدة من الإمساك بي؟
I'm a useless wreck now.
أنا الآن شخص عديم النفع
The Phoenix Heart Token is in Xiao Wuyi's hands.
أمر تشيوه قو بحوزة شياو وو يي
Young Lord Xiao.
ولي العهد شياو
It's been quite some time since you returned from Guazhou.
لقد مضى وقت طويل على عودتك من قواتشو
When will the convicted criminal Cui be transferred to the Court of Judicial Review?
متى ستسلم سجين عائلة تسوي إلى محكمة دالي؟
And where is the Phoenix Heart Token?
وأين أمر تشيوه قو ذاك؟
Your Majesty.
أُبلغ الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Cui Jun was abducted.
تسوي جيون، قد اُختطف
When did this happen?
متى حدث هذا؟
And where was he abducted?
وأين اختُطف؟
It was 5 days ago.
قبل خمسة أيام
I'm still searching for him.
ما زلت أبحث عنه
He was abducted 5 days ago,
لقد هرب قبل خمسة أيام
so why didn't you report it?
لماذا لم تُبلغ عن ذلك؟
Do you have any regard for the laws of Ye?
هل ما زلت تحترم قوانين مملكة يه الكبرى؟
Or could it be that
أم أن تسوي جيون
you hid Cui Jun away yourself—
كان مختبئًا لديك منذ البداية؟
just like how you silenced Princess Yunzhao
تمامًا كما قتلت الأميرة
and stole her Phoenix Heart Token?
وسرقت أمر تشيوه قو الخاص بها
Vice Minister Qi, you seem eager to pin a crime on me.
نائب الوزير تشي مستعجل جدًا لإلصاق التهم بي
I have long submitted a memorial confessing my fault
لقد رفعت منذ وقت طويل مذكرة الاعتراف بالذنب
over Cui Jun's disappearance.
بسبب هروب تسوي جيون
Deliver this memorial to the Department of State Affairs.
أرسل مذكرة الاعتراف بالذنب إلى ديوان الشؤون الإمبراطورية
Remember, slip it in among the daily greetings memorials
تذكر، ضعها بين مذكرات التحية اليومية
so it draws no attention.
حتى لا تلفت الأنظار
Understood.
أمرك
I know the Cui Family Case is of great importance,
أعلم أن قضية عائلة تسوي أمر جلل
but I haven't heard anything from the Department of State Affairs.
لكن ديوان الشؤون الإمبراطورية لم يرد بأي خبر
I was wondering myself—
كنت أتساءل أيضًا
how is it that Cui Jun has disappeared,
كيف أن تسوي جيون قد فُقد
yet the court doesn't seem concerned at all?
والبلاط الإمبراطوري لا يبدو قلقًا على الإطلاق
As a witness in the Cui Family Case,
بصفتي شاهدًا في قضية عائلة تسوي
I've been waiting for the court deliberation.
فأنا ما زلت أنتظر مناقشتها في مجلس البلاط
Vice Minister Qi.
نائب الوزير تشي
You've gone and accused me of silencing Princess Yunzhao.
تتهمني منذ لحظة وصولك بأنني قتلت الأميرة لإسكاتها
Do you have any evidence?
فهل لديك دليل؟
Might I charge you with lodging a false accusation?
ألا يُعد هذا اتهامًا باطلًا؟
You...
...أنت
Anyway, Cui Jun disappeared while he was in your custody.
على أي حال، لقد أضعت تسوي جيون وهو في عهدتك
Enough. You are both loyal and righteous ministers.
يكفي، كلاكما من الوزراء المخلصين للدولة
There is no need to blame each other.
فلا داعي لتبادل الاتهامات
Your Majesty, what I mean is that
أيتها الإمبراطورة الأرملة، أعتقد
Young Lord Xiao deliberately concealed the Phoenix Heart Token's whereabouts.
أن ولي العهد شياو يتعمد إخفاء أمر تشيوه قو
Now that Princess Yunzhao fell dead
الآن وقد توفيت الأميرة فجأة
and Cui Jun has disappeared without a trace,
واختفى تسوي جيون
if it weren't for Empress Wenxi appearing to you in a dream,
لولا أن جلالتك حلمتِ بإمبراطورة ونشي
we would all
لبقينا جميعًا مغيبين عن الحقيقة
remain kept in the dark by him.
بسببه
I believe there's definitely more to
أعتقد أن وفاة الأميرة
Princess Yunzhao's death than meets the eye.
ليست بالأمر البسيط قطعًا
I respectfully request that Your Majesty conduct a thorough investigation.
ألتمس من الإمبراطورة الأرملة التحقيق في الأمر بدقة
Grand Tutor Xie.
المعلم الأكبر شيه
Since Vice Minister Qi insists
يصر نائب الوزير تشي
there's more to Princess Yunzhao's death,
على أن وفاة الأميرة مشبوهة
would you support a thorough investigation
هل ترغب في دعم تحقيق شامل
to seek justice for Princess Yunzhao?
لإحقاق العدالة للأميرة؟
If there is evidence,
إذا كان هناك دليل
then naturally it should be investigated.
فبالطبع يجب التحقيق
Since this is merely an accusation
إن كانت مجرد ادعاءات
with no evidence,
ولا يوجد أي دليل
let's put the matter of Princess Yunzhao aside for now.
فلنضع قضية الأميرة جانبًا في الوقت الحالي
Young Lord Xiao.
يا ولي العهد شياو
Do you have Cui Jun's Phoenix Heart Token in your possession?
هل أمر تشيوه قو الخاص بتسوي جيون بحوزتك؟
Don't tell me it was snatched away
لا تقل إن الأمر
along with Cui Jun when he was abducted.
اختفى مع اختفاء صاحبه أيضًا؟
No, it wasn't.
كلا، لم يحدث ذلك
The Phoenix Heart Token
أمر تشيوه قو
is indeed in my possession.
بحوزتي بالفعل
So it's in his possession?
إنه بحوزته
Is that the Phoenix Heart Token?
هل ذلك هو أمر تشيوه قو؟
Everyone, please take a look.
أيها السادة، تفضلوا بالنظر
This is the Phoenix Heart Token that Cui Jun had.
هذا هو أمر تشيوه قو الذي كان بحوزة تسوي جيون
I wonder if when Empress Wenxi appeared in your dream,
أتساءل عندما ظهرت لكِ إمبراطورة ونشي في المنام
was this the piece she showed you, Your Majesty?
هل هذا هو ما عرضته على جلالتكِ؟
Since you all wish to see it so badly,
بما أنكم جميعًا حريصون جدًا على رؤيته
why not pass it around?
فما المانع من تمريره بينكم؟
It doesn't seem all that special.
لا يبدو أن به شيئًا مميزًا
Isn't this just an ordinary token? How could it deserve the saying
أليس مجرد أمر عادي؟
"when the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world"?
فكيف يقال إن "بظهور تشيوه قو يستتب السلام في العالم"؟
It is said the Cui family's private mines
يقال إن منجم عائلة تسوي السري
were discovered because of this Phoenix Heart Token.
قد اكتُشف بسبب أمر تشيوه قو هذا
In your opinion, Young Lord Xiao,
برأيك يا ولي العهد
after Cui Jun has finally been brought to justice
تسوي جيون ارتكب الكثير من الشرور
after having committed countless crimes, who should this Token be handed over to?
بعد أن يتم إعدامه، لمن يجب تسليم أمر تشيوه قو هذا؟
Did Empress Wenxi not mention this
عندما ظهرت إمبراطورة ونشي في حلمك
to Your Majesty when she appeared in your dream?
ألم تذكر ذلك لجلالتك؟
"Under Heaven,
كل ما تحت السماء
all land belongs to the ruler;
ملك للإمبراطور
within the realm,
وكل من يعيش على هذه الأرض
all people are the ruler's subjects.
رعيته
Yet unfair divisions burden the officials,
لا عدل عند كبار القوم في توزيع العمل
while I alone toil tirelessly.
كأنما خُلقتُ وحدي لأشقى بالواجب
Praise that I am not yet worn with age,
أثنوا عليّ لأني لم أشيخ بعد
still strong and vigorous.
فأنا ما زلت في أوج قوتي
With robust strength, I oversee all corners of the realm."
بقوتي البدنية، أدير شؤون الأقطار الأربعة
I hope Your Majesty will have sympathy for the Beifu troops
آمل من الإمبراطورة الأرملة أن تراعي تضحيات جنود جيش الشمال
who fight without regard for their lives,
فهم يضحون بحياتهم
yet suffer from shoddy weaponry.
لكنهم يعانون من رداءة أسلحتهم
I respectfully request that the copper and iron mines
لذلك أرجو تخصيص ما تم مصادرته
confiscated from the Cui family's private mines
من النحاس والحديد في منجم عائلة تسوي السري
be allocated to the Beifu Army
لجيش الشمال
to upgrade their armaments.
لتطوير أسلحتهم
Please rise, Young Lord Xiao.
انهض يا ولي العهد شياو
What you speak makes perfect sense.
ما هذا الذي تقوله يا ولي العهد؟
The Beifu soldiers are warriors of our great Ye.
جنود جيش الشمال هم جنود مملكتي يه الكبرى
I approved your Beifu Reform
إن موافقتي على إصلاحات ولي العهد لجيش الشمال
precisely to forge a more elite, formidable army.
من أجل الحصول على جنود نخبة وقادة أقوياء
Moreover, you've rendered meritorious service
علاوة على ذلك، لقد قدمت خدمة جليلة بكشف قضية عائلة تسوي
in cracking the Cui Family Case and deserve a reward.
وتستحق المكافأة
I find your request
أرى أن طلبك
most reasonable.
مناسب للغاية
The Cui family's private mines shall be dedicated to
سيتم استخدام منجم عائلة تسوي السري لتحسين
upgrading the Beifu Army's weaponry.
أسلحة جيش الشمال
On behalf of the Beifu soldiers,
باسم جنود جيش الشمال
I thank Your Majesty for your benevolent grace.
أشكر الإمبراطورة الأرملة على كرمها
Xiao Wuyi!
شياو وو يي
How dare you mock me?
أتجرؤ على خداعي؟
Where's the Phoenix Heart Token?
أين أمر تشيوه قو؟
How could this be?
كيف يمكن هذا؟
How come it's empty?
كيف يمكن أن يكون فارغًا؟
I have no idea.
لا أعلم يا صاحبة الجلالة
The Phoenix Heart Token
قبل قليل، كان أمر تشيوه قو
was right here in this brocade box just moments ago.
داخل هذا الصندوق
All the officials in the court saw it.
وقد رآه جميع المسؤولين في البلاط
-Yeah, we all saw it. -How could it be gone?
لقد رأيناه جميعًا - كيف اختفى؟ -
There's no way.
مستحيل
Exactly.
نعم
Everyone saw it. It needs to be thoroughly investigated.
لقد رأيناه جميعًا - يجب التحقيق في الأمر بدقة -
Your Majesty.
أُبلغ جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
I noticed
لقد رأيت للتو
that when His Highness turned around,
أميرة بينغنينغ وهي تسرق أمر تشيوه قو
Princess Pingning stole the Phoenix Heart Token.
عندما استدار ولي العهد
I didn't! You're slandering me!
لم أفعل، أنتِ تفترين عليّ
Doing that in front of everyone here— do you think I'm crazy?
هل أنا مجنونة لأفعل ذلك أمام الجميع؟
Whether you have it or not, we'll know after a search.
هل فعلتِ ذلك أم لا، سنعرف بعد تفتيشك
Search her.
فتشوها
Your Majesty!
جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
I didn't...
لم أسرقه
I didn't. I...
...لم أفعل... أنا
It was really on her. It really was.
إنه معها حقًا - إنه معها -
Your Majesty!
يا جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Your Majesty, that's impossible!
يا جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة، هذا مستحيل
I was framed.
لقد تم تدبير الأمر لي
I-I didn't take it!
أنا... أنا لم آخذه
Your Majesty.
يا جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
May I borrow the brocade box?
هل يمكنني استعارة هذا الصندوق للحظة؟
Granted.
مسموح
There's a hidden compartment?
هناك حجرة سرية أخرى به
You...
...أنتِ
That's right.
هذا صحيح
You didn't take Cui Jun's token.
الأمر الخاص بتسوي جيون هذا أنتِ لم تأخذيه بالفعل
Because the one that fell out of you
لأن الأمر الذي سقط منكِ
was my mother's.
هو ملك والدتي
Princess Yunzhao's?
ملك الأميرة؟
Why did she have Princess Yunzhao's token?
كيف يمكن أن تكون لديها أمر الأميرة؟
Exactly.
نعم
Please forgive me, Your Majesty,
أطلب العفو يا جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
for contriving this contraption to conceal the Phoenix Heart Token
لقد قمتُ بصنع هذه الآلية وأخفيتُ أمر تشيوه قو
and deceiving you.
وخدعت جلالتكِ
I did so only to retrieve the token on Princess Pingning
فقط من أجل العثور على هذا الأمر الذي بحوزة الآنسة
and uncover the truth behind my mother's death.
والتحقيق في سبب وفاة والدتي
I'm innocent.
أنا مظلومة
That Phoenix Heart Token didn't belong to Princess Yunzhao.
أمر تشيوه قو ذاك ليس ملك الأميرة
What makes you say so?
على أي أساس تقولين إنه ليس ملكها؟
Could it be that you've seen my mother's token?
هل سبق لكِ أن رأيتِ أمر تشيوه قو الخاص بوالدتي؟
When?
متى؟
Li Lejun.
لي له جيون
You murdered Princess Yunzhao for the Phoenix Heart Token.
لقد قتلتِ الأميرة للاستيلاء على أمر تشيوه قو
The Phoenix Heart Token on you
وأمر تشيوه قو الذي بحوزتك
is the most compelling evidence of your guilt.
هو أكبر دليل على جريمتك
It's not like that.
الأمر ليس كذلك
It's not...
لا
It seems
يبدو أن
Princess Yunzhao's death is indeed suspicious.
وراء وفاة الأميرة سر مريب حقًا
It's fake.
إنه مزيف
That Phoenix Heart Token is fake.
أمر تشيوه قو ذاك مزيف
It was forged, Your Majesty!
إنه مقلّد، يا جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Your Majesty.
أُبلغ جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
I've heard that the Phoenix Heart Tokens
بلغني أن أمر تشيوه قو
were cast from the Phoenix Imperial Seal
صُنع من صهر ختم العنقاء
of Empress Wenxi.
الخاص بإمبراطورة ونشي
Though the carvings can be replicated,
معدن ختم العنقاء فريد
the unique material of the Phoenix Imperial Seal
يمكن تقليد النقش
cannot be faked.
لكن لا يمكن تقليد المعدن
Whether it's genuine or not,
هل هو حقيقي أم مزيف
we need only compare the two Phoenix Heart Tokens.
سنعرف بمقارنة الأمرين
Cui Jun's, Prince Jing'an's.
أمر تسوي جيون، وأمر الأمير شياو الأكبر
And this one...
ماذا عن هذه القطعة؟
This one belongs to Crown Prince Wenxi.
هذه ملك ولي عهد ونشي
The engraving on it
النقش عليها
was carved by my mother herself.
نقشته والدتي الإمبراطورة بنفسها
This one is the "Phoenix Head" token.
هذا هو رأس تشيوه
It holds command over the other 3 Phoenix Heart Tokens.
الذي يستطيع إصدار الأوامر لبقية الأوامر الثلاثة
Are you truly willing to take out one of the tokens
هل ستُخرج حقًا أمر تشيوه قو
to play along with me in this act?
لمشاركتي في هذه الخطة؟
Right now, the world only knows of
الآن، لا يعرف الناس
the 2 tokens held by Cui Jun and my mother.
سوى بالقطعتين اللتين بحوزة تسوي جيون ووالدتي
They have no idea that the rest are in your possession.
ولا يعلمون أن البقية بحوزتك
Once you reveal it,
بمجرد أن تخرجه
at the very least Grand Tutor and Li Mao will learn that
سيعرف المعلم الأكبر ولي ماو على الأقل
Prince Jing'an was also a token holder.
أن الأمير شياو الأكبر كان أحد حاملي الأمر
Your identity
وهويتك
might be exposed.
قد تنكشف
What goes around comes around.
كل سبب نال جزاءه
Debts of gratitude and vengeance must be repaid.
وكل ثأر قد سُويَ حسابُه
It's just a token, after all.
إنه مجرد أمر
If it can bring the murderer to justice,
إذا كان سيؤدي إلى معاقبة القاتل
then it's worth it.
فالأمر يستحق
It's indeed genuine.
إنه حقيقي بالفعل
No way.
كيف يعقل هذا؟
It was you.
إنه أنت
Xiao Wuyi, so you also have a Phoenix Heart Token.
شياو وو يي، أنت أيضًا تملك أمر تشيوه قو
Princess Pingning,
يا أميرة بينغنينغ
what do you mean by "also"?
ماذا تقصدين بـ "أيضًا"؟
That Phoenix Heart Token is yours.
أمر تشيوه قو ذاك ملكك
You used your own token
لقد استخدمت أمرك الخاص
to help Jiayu frame me.
لمساعدة جيا يوي في الإيقاع بي
Princess Pingning,
يا أميرة بينغنينغ
do you truly think I, Xiao Wuyi, am some kind of saint
هل تظنين حقًا أنني قديس؟
Everyone knows that
كما يعلم الجميع
the Phoenix Heart Tokens contain secrets about hidden mineral deposits.
أوامر تشيوه قو تخفي مواقع المناجم
Tell me, which one of you here
اسمحوا لي أن أسألكم أيها الحضور
would not want them?
من منكم لا يريده؟
If I had a Phoenix Heart Token,
لو كنت أملك أمر تشيوه قو
why wouldn't I keep it hidden
لماذا لا أخفيه جيدًا
and secretly mine the resources?
وأستخرج المعادن سرًا
Why would I bring it out in front of all the court officials
بدلًا من أن أظهره أمام جميع مسؤولي البلاط
just to frame you?
لأوقع بكِ
Who do you think you are?
من تكونين أنتِ؟
I'd like to ask all of you present:
اسمحوا لي أن أسألكم أيها الحضور
does anyone truly believe I, Xiao Wuyi,
هل تصدقون حقًا أنني، شياو وو يي
would be so selfless and generous?
سأكون بهذا الكرم؟
Your Majesty, besides the Phoenix Heart Token,
يا صاحبة الجلالة بالإضافة إلى أمر تشيوه قو
I also have a witness.
لدي شاهد أيضًا
Summon them.
أحضروه
This is Ms. Yang, the coachman's wife.
أحضرت السيدة يانغ، زوجة السائس
They saw nothing to begin with
هم في الأصل لم يروا شيئًا
and were no witnesses at all.
ولم يكونوا شهودًا
But after you abducted them,
لكن بعد أن اختطفتِهم
they ended up becoming witnesses against you.
أصبحوا شهودًا
She...
هي
She asked me where I was
سألتني في يوم الحادث
between 3 to 4 a.m. on the day of the incident,
أين كنت في تمام الثالثة فجرًا؟
and whether I had been to the stable.
وهل ذهبت إلى الإسطبل
After learning that I had not yet gotten up,
وعندما علمت أنني لم أكن قد استيقظت بعد
she asked no further questions.
لم تسأل أي شيء آخر
That must've been the very hour you snuck into the stables
إذًا هذا هو الوقت الذي تسللتِ فيه إلى الإسطبل
to slip the poison, wasn't it?
لوضع السُم، أليس كذلك؟
Let's go.
هيا
Wait.
مهلًا
Don't commit any more killing.
لا ترتكبي المزيد من جرائم القتل
I really should've killed them all.
كان يجب القضاء عليهم من الجذور
Princess Pingning murdered my mother
أميرة بينغنينغ، من أجل الاستيلاء أمر تشيوه قو
to seize the Phoenix Heart Token.
قتلت والدتي
Please seek justice for my mother, Your Majesty.
أرجوكِ يا صاحبة الجلالة أن تنصفي والدتي
These pieces of evidence are not enough to convict Lejun.
هذه الأدلة لا تكفي لإدانة له جيون
Further investigation is needed.
الأمر يتطلب تحقيقًا شاملًا
Please deliberate this matter with caution, Your Majesty.
أرجو من جلالتكِ التروي في الأمر
Prince Qi, are you trying
هل يعقل أن سمو أمير تشي
to cover up for Princess Pingning?
يريد التستر على أميرة بينغنينغ؟
If Princess Pingning truly feels wronged,
إذا كانت أميرة بينغنينغ تشعر بالظلم حقًا
we might as well have the entire Eastern Palace thoroughly searched
فلتسمح بتفتيش القصر الشرقي
to prove her innocence.
لإثبات براءتها
Your Majesty.
جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
-Your Majesty! -I...
‫- الإمبراطورة الأرملة أنا -
I plead guilty.
أنا أعترف بذنبي
Lejun!
له جيون
It was me.
أنا من فعلتها
I murdered Princess Yunzhao
أنا من أجل الحصول على أمر تشيوه قو الخاص بالأميرة
to seize her Phoenix Heart Token.
قتلتها
Please punish me, Your Majesty.
أرجو من صاحبة الجلالة معاقبتي
He Tian.
خه تيان
Guards.
أيها الحراس
That day,
في ذلك اليوم
you suddenly had a stomachache and needed to lie down.
شعرتِ فجأة بألم في بطنك واحتجتِ إلى الاستلقاء
I was the one who drugged you.
أنا من وضعت لكِ الدواء
What's wrong?
ماذا بكِ؟
Mother,
أمي
I feel a little unwell.
أشعر أنني متعبة
Your Highness, why don't we share a ride?
سمو الأميرة، لمَ لا تركبين معي؟
I spared you
فقط لأنني كنت أفكر فيكِ
only because I did not wish to drag you into this.
ولم أرغب في توريطك
If I had been ruthless enough
لو كنت أكثر قسوة
to strike directly at your carriage with Princess Yunzhao inside
وهاجمت عربتك أنتِ والأميرة مباشرة
and send both of you to your deaths,
وجعلتكما تموتان معًا
none of this would have happened today, would it?
لما حدث ما حدث اليوم، أليس كذلك؟
Lejun!
!له جيون
Your Majesty.
جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Princess Yunzhao did not die as a criminal.
لم تمت الأميرة وهي مذنبة
This token
هذا الأمر
was left to her by Empress Wenxi.
تركته إمبراطورة ونشي للأميرة
Now that she's passed away
لقد توفيت
and had divorced Grand Tutor Xie,
وتطلقت من المعلم الأكبر شيه
this token
فمن حق نسلها
should rightfully be inherited by her offspring.
أن يرث هذا الأمر
So, according to you, Young Lord Xiao,
إذًا، برأي ولي العهد شياو
-we should... -The whereabouts of the remaining
...من المفترض أن - ‫- بقية أوامر تشيوه قو
Phoenix Heart Tokens are still unknown.
ما زال مجهولًا تمامًا في حوزةِ من تكون
If Your Majesty were to claim them all for yourself
أمام جميع مسؤولي البلاط
in front of the entire court,
إذا فكرتِ جلالتكِ في أخذ الأمران لنفسها
I'm afraid the remaining token holders
أخشى أن حاملي القطع المتبقية
would never come forward.
لن يظهروا مرة أخرى أبدًا
As for whether it should go to Grand Tutor Xie or Xie Jiayu—
هل ستعطينها للمعلم الأكبر شيه أم لشيه جيا يوي؟
the choice is Your Majesty's.
جلالتكِ من ستختاري
Come to me.
تعالي إلى جانبي
Good girl.
يا ابنتي الطيبة
You've really been through a lot.
لقد عانيتِ كثيرًا حقًا
Your devotion to capturing the murderer who killed your mother
إمساككِ بالقاتل من أجل والدتك المتوفاة
speaks volumes of your filial piety.
يُظهر مدى بركِ بها
This Phoenix Heart Token
أمر تشيوه قو هذا
was originally left to Princess Yunzhao by Empress Wenxi.
تركته إمبراطورة ونشي للأميرة في الأصل
Now that she's passed away,
والآن بعد أن رحلت الأميرة
it's only right that you keep it.
من الطبيعي أن تحتفظي به أنتِ
Thank you for your gracious kindness, Your Majesty.
أشكر جلالة الإمبراطورة الأرملة على فضلها
Should the secrets of the Phoenix Heart Token ever be uncovered,
إذا تم كشف سر أوامر تشيوه قو لاحقًا
I'll present this token to our great Ye without hesitation.
سأقدم هذا الأمر بكل سرور لمملكة يه الكبرى
What a good girl.
!يا لكِ من فتاة جيدة
From now on, come to the palace more often with Yuanji.
في المستقبل، تعالي إلى القصر كثيرًا مع يوان جي
Yes, Your Majesty.
أمركِ
Xiao Wuyi.
شياو وو يي
You forced me to personally send
لقد دفعتموني لإرسال أختي بيدي
my own sister to prison.
إلى السجن
She committed murder,
إنها قاتلة
and the victim was none other than Xie Jiayu's mother.
بل وقتلت والدة شيه جيا يوي
You know perfectly well why she did it.
أنت تعلم جيدًا لماذا قتلت
She did it to protect me.
لقد فعلت ذلك لحمايتي
Protect you?
حمايتك؟
You both live in fear of Crown Prince Wenxi's return,
أنتم تخافون من ظهور ولي عهد ونشي
but Crown Prince Wenxi
لكن ولي عهد ونشي
died 20 years ago!
قد مات بالفعل قبل عشرين عامًا
If it weren't for Princess Yunzhao saving Li Lejun with her medical skills,
لولا مهارات الأميرة الطبية التي أنقذتها
Li Lejun's condition would never have improved,
لما كانت لي له جيون شُفيت من مرضها
and she wouldn't have lived until now.
وما كانت لتعيش حتى الآن
And yet, because of a little suspicion,
فقط من أجل شك بسيط
a fleeting fear,
وقليل من الخوف
she could raise her blade against the very person who saved her.
رفعت السيف في وجه من أحسنت إليها
Tell me, did Li Lejun do nothing wrong?
ألم تخطئ لي له جيون؟
Once she chose to act,
بما أنها هي من بدأت
she must bear the consequences.
فعليها أن تتحمل العواقب
Li Yizhi, as the Regent,
لي يي تشي، بصفتك الوصي على العرش
you're supposed to know right from wrong
يجب أن تميز بين الصواب والخطأ
and where the line must be drawn!
وأين تكمن الحدود
Right from wrong?
!الصواب والخطأ
Do you dare say that you helped Xie Jiayu
أتجرؤ على القول إنك ساعدت شيه جيا يوي
without any selfish motives?
دون أي دافع أناني؟
How insolent of you.
إذًا فأنت متعجرف للغاية
You know how much I couldn't bear to part with Yaoyao.
أنت تعلم جيدًا مدى تعلقي بجيا يوي
Now that you've driven my sister into jail,
والآن دفعت أختي إلى السجن
you still expect me to continue being friends with you
وتتوقع مني أن أستمر في معاملتك كأخ
and push forward with the reform together?
وأن أواصل معك تنفيذ الإصلاحات؟
No such easy bargain exists
في هذا العالم
in this world!
أين تجد أمرًا بهذه المثالية؟
Your Highness Prince Qi!
سمو أمير تشي
If you must find someone to blame
إذا كان لا بد من وجود شخص تحمله المسؤولية
to make yourself feel better,
حتى تشعر بالراحة في قلبك
you can hate me.
فيمكنك أن تكرهني
But Li Yizhi,
لكن يا لي يي تشي
you, too, rose from the ranks of the displaced commoners.
أنت أيضًا خرجت من بين عامة الناس واللاجئين
Since you've chosen to sit in this position,
بما أنك قررت الجلوس على هذا الكرسي
you should have a more compassionate heart
يجب أن يكون لديك قلب أكثر رحمة
and broader aspirations.
وطموح أوسع
The road ahead is long.
الطريق طويل وشاق
Do not let fear and desire consume you
لا تدع الخوف والرغبة يسيطران عليك
and make you forget the path you once walked.
وتنسى الطريق الذي أتيت منه
Is Crown Prince Wenxi
ولي عهد ونشي
really dead?
هل مات حقًا؟
He's dead.
لقد مات
He died long ago,
مات منذ زمن طويل
and he'll never come back.
ولن يعود أبدًا